Okay, good took a while to write so essentially
what we do is we start off with K arms right
and then in the first round okay so median
elimination is going to proceed in rounds
okay. In the first round we pull each arm
some number of times right determined by this
magic quantity. So can people read this magic
quantity it is 1 by epsilon l by two the whole
squared, better? log 3 by delta l okay.
So I pull each arm that many number of times
okay and then I estimate their empirical value
right Q l a I will estimate it where l indicates
that this is the Q function I am forming at
the lth stage okay. Then what I do is I take
these Q l a, arrange them in ascending, descending
whatever order I find the median of all these
arms. And then eliminate all those arms whose
values is below the median right I am eliminating.
So this is the set difference so I take my
current set S l, right these are all the arms
that are under consideration.
So S1 will be all the arms and then I am eliminating
all those arms such that so my Q l a is less
than ml where ml is the median at the lth
level right. And then I change my constants
by magic amounts again. So my epsilon l plus
1 becomes three-fourths of epsilon l, epsilon
l itself started as epsilon by four okay.
Now it becomes 3/4 of epsilon by four and
my delta l plus 1 becomes delta l by 2 which
already started as delta by 2 so it becomes
delta by 4, and l equals l plus 1 and I keep
going until my S l becomes 1, the number of
arms left becomes one right. So how many rounds
will I go log K rounds because every time
I am eliminating half the arms right, because
I am looking at the median and I am eliminating
everything below the median.
So I am guaranteed to eliminate half the arms
in every round, so I will end in log K rounds
okay. But the trick to provide proving any
kind of sample complexity here is to show
that okay, this quantity right when I sum
it over this log K rounds is some bounded
quantity right and that gives me the sample
complexity I want.
I have already told you what the sample complexity
is going to be, what was it K by epsilon square
log 1 by delta, some constant by delta, so
as far as order notations we can ignore the
constant so log 1 by delta. So that is what
this is going to be the sample complexity,
so I will have to show you that first. Second
in fact first I will have to show you that
this is actually a pac algorithm right, that
it actually gives you a epsilon optimal arm
with a high probability right.
It becomes a little tricky here, because I
am eliminating half the arms every times.
So now I will have to think about what is
the probability that I have eliminated all
the epsilon optimal arms right. So I have
to, in some round along the way before I reach
the final round okay I should not eliminate
all the epsilon optimal arms right.
So what we will do is you see that right,
because at the end of the thing if that one
arm left is some epsilon optimal arm, I am
safe right if along the way if I eliminate
all the epsilon optimal arms then I am in
trouble. Right so what I will do now is to
show that at every round the probability of
me doing that is very small.
So small that when I add up the probability
of me eliminating across all the rounds it
is still below delta right it is still below
delta so that is essentially what I am going
to try and show did that make sense. So at
every round the probability of me eliminating
all the epsilon optimal arms is small, so
small that when I add it up across all the
rounds it is still less than delta okay. So
that is essentially what I am going to what
I am going to show.
Okay so first theorem that I will state it,
but I will come back and prove this later
is the
median elimination algorithm with takes epsilon,
delta this is epsilon delta pac okay. So we
will prove this in two parts the first lemma
will help us establish that okay, and then
we will have another result later that will
help us establish the sample complexity.
Sample complexity is actually trivial right
if you think about it, it is essentially summing
this quantity up right starting from epsilon
by four and delta by two and successively
changing the value of epsilon and delta okay.
It is just a bunch of algebra right you just
move numbers around and simplify things you
will get it conceptually there is nothing
deep about looking at the sample complexity.
So is that clear, so I essentially have to
sum up this quantity right for every arm.
So this will be multiplied by the size of
the arms which will be, which will start with
K and then it will become K by two, K by four
successively becomes smaller and smaller and
likewise the epsilon and my delta also becomes
smaller and smaller. So the idea is to just
to sum it over l this quantity and then replace
this by a function of epsilon and l. You can
replace epsilon l right by a function of epsilon.
So what is epsilon 1, it is epsilon by four,
what is epsilon 2, three by four into epsilon
by two, epsilon by four, epsilon 3 is three
by four the whole square so epsilon l is essentially
three by four whole power l minus one into
epsilon by four right. So like that so you
can write this a similar expression for delta
and we can essentially simplify right. So
that part is fairly straightforward so if
you have time I will just give you an intuition
into that otherwise you can work it out easily.
Now the first part is one that requires some
work right. So this is what we will do for
every phase l in the median elimination algorithm
we have the probability. So this requires
a little bit of thought, so what I am saying
so what is this, this is the true best arm
at level l right. So at level 1 I would expect
this to be a star right.
So, the true best arm I am not talking about
the capital Q right I am talking about the
q stars here, so I am talking about the true
best arm right. So in this case I would expect
the true this this should be q star a star
right in level 1, but in level 2 itself it
could be something different because I might
have lost a star in the first round itself
right.
What I am saying is okay this is the best
I could have done in the lth round right potentially
right, and what is this, this is the best
I could have done in the l plus 1 th round
right. So the bad case is when this is less
than that, right that means I have eliminated
some high-ranking arms well all I have left
are low ranking arms right.
So the bad case is when this quantity is less
than that quantity right by how much it should
be less right, that is the question that is
the trick we are asking here. So if I add
an epsilon to this so essentially I have my,
hmm, I dont know, let us call this j star
right that is the maximum in the lth level.
So I have my q star j star here and I have
my q star i star here which is the guy that
gives me the max here right.
If I add an epsilon to this if I add an epsilon
to this and this is within that that means
this is epsilon optimal when you can consider
against that right, do you see that if I add
an epsilon to this lower value and the higher
value is actually less than that then it is
an acceptable situation, because the lower
value is within epsilon of the higher value
correct, so this is a good outcome.
So I am saying the probability of the good
outcome is at least 1 minus delta l that means
the probability is high okay, does it make
sense the probability of the good outcome
is at least 1 minus delta okay. Now the thing
to notice here is this is not truly epsilon,
this is epsilon l right and this is not delta,
this is delta l, so why is that the case because
every round I will lose epsilon l, right at
most epsilon l right.
So at the end of the day I should not have
lost more than epsilon right. So what I am
going to show you is that every round I will
lose epsilon l and my epsilon l is chosen
such that even if i lose the epsilon l for
every l, overall loss will be epsilon right.
So that because we know that when the S, in
S1 the best number is a star right.
And if the overall loss is less than epsilon,
then at the end of this I will have at least
1 epsilon optimal arm left okay, so that is
basically what we are trying to show here.
So this relation makes sense why we are trying
to show this okay. And likewise this 1 minus
delta l is there because at the end of the
day if all the events hold true also my probability
must be at least 1 minus delta right.
Therefore, we use delta l and that is the
reason your epsilon 1 and delta 1 are already
smaller than epsilon and delta, because if
I start off with epsilon here and delta here
I am gone okay. So people know what wlog means
right, without loss of generality I am going
to consider l equal to one right. So whatever
results I show here will will hold for the
subsequent l right.
So we start off by looking at the first, the
event E1 which is
first thing I am looking at it I am grossly
under estimating the true value right. I mean
this should now start looking familiar to
you, because in everything we have been doing
the same thing we start off by say okay, first
thing that has to go wrong is I grossly underestimate
the true optimal actions value.
And then we will think about okay what happens
if I overestimate the sub optimal actions
value but I start off by say okay grossly
underestimate this right. So now what is the
probability of this, and we already have our
magic number here, so substitute everything
and tell me, so you have the expression here
right and you have the magic number there.
Right this guy will get cancelled out, again
do you have a 4 problem there yeah yeah so
well the square should be outside I mean I
am just writing it down from the algorithm
here, so their results are wrong right. So
it should be epsilon l squared by two not
epsilon l by two the whole squared and this
is a one-sided bound. So the outside 2 will
not be there, right so everything will simplify
and you will get delta 1 by 3 right.
Okay, this is the first event. Suppose it
does not hold okay, suppose E1 does not hold
essentially I have not made a bad mistake
under estimating the best arm right. And since
it is maybe I should have done it slightly
differently I have said without loss of generality
consider l equal to one, but then I put in
a star here which actually violates the without
loss of generality part okay.
So the a star here is actually the best arm
left at level l that is how we should think
of it, it is not the overall based arm, whatever
be the level l it is the best arm left at
level l and for l equal to 1 it happens to
be a star, the true a star right for l equal
to 2 , 3 and 4 this will essentially become
the best arm at that level.
So I will just put a l there so that you know
what I mean okay. This is the best arm in
the lth level that is left among all the arms
that is left the true best arm in the lth
level okay. So next I am going to look at
the probability that, hmm, this one I should
put the 2 in the numerator is it what do you
need for it to cancel out.
Epsilon1 by 2, so epsilon1 by 4 no yeah, so
this is epsilon by 2 so substitute that I
get epsilon squared by four, right that will
become half so that is 1 by epsilon squared
by 2 so I will get that things are all fine
okay good. So I am going to look at this problem
right, so sorry not this, so E1 does not hold
that means that this is kept true right. So
E1 is the event where I have underestimated
this so I am saying E1 does not hold that
means that it is no longer an underestimate.
So this is my estimate is within epsilon by
2 right, but then I am looking at the possibility
that yeah, so with my some jth arm which is
not epsilon1 optimal right. So that is a condition,
no, right I know that my current estimate
in the lth round I am going to decide about
eliminating in the lth round right in the
current round I am not underestimated my a
star l okay.
So I am within epsilon of that with epsilon1
by 2 of the true a star value right, but then
I take some other arm j which is a bad arm,
bad in the sense j is not epsilon l close
to a star, it is a bad arm right. And I figure
out what is the probability that the Q estimate
for that arm will be greater than the Q estimate
for the a star right.
So if this happens right, then there is a
chance that a star will get eliminated only
a chance right, why it has to be in the lower
half not just get beaten by one guy but it
has to be in the lower half of the arms right.
So I need at least K by two or whatever the
size of S l by 2 bad arms to beat me correct,
for me to eliminate this arm.
Right I need at least half of the arms to
beat me not just one arm right, but before
we go to that part, so what is the probability
of this happening. Well so this conditioning
tells us that Q l a star is not too bad right.
So what does that mean Q l j has to be more
than epsilon by 2 so you remember that figure
we drew right.
So either this has to be under estimate, well
I erased the figure, but either the a star
has to be underestimated by more than epsilon
by 2 or the a prime has to be over-estimated
by more than epsilon by 2 right, here we are
conditioning it on the event that a star is
not underestimated by more than epsilon by
2. Therefore, j has to be over-estimated by
more than epsilon by 2.
Right since this event we have conditioned
it as false, so that event has to be true
okay. So what do we get in that case same
thing here right, so I am kind of skipping
a step here but people are all fine with that
right, I am skipping, rewriting this bound
right. So essentially you will have to now
replace this with over estimating by epsilon
by 2 right. In fact I should probably just
make you write that missing step as a homework.
So that I am sure that people are all comfortable
with the notation nothing more the notation
can get really complex, otherwise the concepts
are very simple, that is why I am taking so
much time talking over it and if I could just
write the proof and leave it at that because
it is fairly easy, these things are fairly
easy. So this is for one arm right and like
this I have K arms right, so the probability
hmm good.
So let now use the same symbols here, I do
not agree with, let hash bad be the number
of bad arms okay, hash bad be the number of
bad arms such that this this condition holds
right hash bad be the number of bad arms such
that, that condition holds. So these are the
number of bad arms that are beating the best
arm.
So what will that expectation be? Mod S l
by 2..yeah, not really but I agree with the
mod S l part but not S l by 2 I have a probability
for that happening right. And how many such
experiments I actually its mod S l minus 1
right potentially everything other than the
best arm could be a bad arm right maximum
thing is S l minus 1 right.
And so it is S l minus 1 into delta1 by 3,
so that is the probability of one arm being
bad, one arm actually for which this first
relation holds for one bad arm and there are
S l minus 1, I am just making it S l to make
our life easier. So S l such bad arms so the
expected number of bad arms will be S l into
delta1 by 3. Now I want to look at the probability
that hash bad... this is where we are going
to use the Markov inequality right.
So I have already written the expectation
here, so I am asking you the probability of
X greater than equal to a is the expected
value of X divided by a right, so this is
less than or equal to the expected value which
is, divided by a okay. So what have you shown
there is that if E1 does not hold if I am
good in my estimate for the best arm okay,
the probability that half the I mean, so many
bad arms will beat me is bounded by 2 delta1
by 3 right.
But I am also considering E1 as a bad event
right E1 is also bad because my estimate for
the best arm is really bad you know. So all
bets are off in some sense right because I
do not really, I cannot really identify my
best term because it is so bad right, so all
bets are off so E1 is also bad event right
all of this is bad and E1 is also bad.
So what is the total probability of something
bad happening, the two together, but they
are you plug this in if you want to use a
fancy term we use the Union bound and then
we say the probability of something bad happening
is bounded by delta1 right. So this bad is
delta1 by 3, that bad is 2 delta1 by 3 and
this is actually the complementary event of
E1 in fact I can just add the probabilities,
I do not really need the Union bound.
So the total probability of something of bad
happening is delta1 right. So that is essentially
what we are started off by saying here. So
the probability of good is 1 minus delta now
we have shown that the probability of bad
is delta l, so the probability of good is
1 minus delta l okay. Great. So one of the
nice things about the median elimination algorithm
is that it was one of the earliest papers
to introduce this kind of a round based algorithms
to the bandit literature right.
Now a lot of later improvements on both regret
based case and people trying to play around
with the the pac guarantees all have switched
to some kind of round based ideas, you know
so you do a certain number of pulls and then
you eliminate a certain number of arms right,
and then go back and pull the remaining arm
some more and then eliminate some more arms.
So this kind of a round based elimination
methods have become very popular in the bandit
literature and the median elimination is one
of the earliest such round based elimination
approaches then after this it became very
popular and a lot of papers started being
written using this kind of a round based idea
right.
So we have so far what we have shown is that
it is have you shown that it is pac hmm..
what is it that is fine that ..that I have
already spoken about this lemma is taken as
proved right, this lemma is taken as proved,
so yeah you have to still use the Union bound
for every round that I am eliminating right,
so what we have to show is well I have all
these deltas right, so we have to keep adding
them up to make sure that eventually you are
less than overall you are less than delta
right.
So every round the probability of failure
is bounded by delta1 right so for the K rounds
the probability of failure is I mean whatever
the log K rounds the probability of failure
is bounded by summing it up. So delta by 2,
delta by 4, delta by 8 and so on so forth
until you reach 1 right, so that is the summation
and or not until you reach 1, until you reach
log K rounds.
So you will get delta by 2 power logK okay,
and the summation of that will go to delta
right it is essentially delta into half plus
one fourth plus one eighth right .. if that
sum runs to infinity you will get one, but
the sum is not running to infinity it stops
at some finite time, so it will be less than
1, so the summation will be less than delta
proved right.
So some probability of something bad happening
will be less than delta. So likewise you can
show these same things for the epsilon right,
so at every level you drop utmost by epsilon
l right. So the total you would have dropped
is epsilon by 4 plus so it is essentially
one-fourth plus what is it three-fourth into
one or epsilon by 4 into one plus one-fourth
and so on so forth right.
Three by four l minus 1 yeah yeah that is
also upper bounded by 1 if you run it to infinity
no its not..yeah it is upper bounded by one
if you run that summation to infinity but
you are stopping at some finite amount so
it will be less than epsilon okay. So both
of that are satisfied that is easy enough,
the harder, the trickier part is to show the
sample complexity right.
It is not hard, it is just algebra can you
let you guys do it or you want me to do the
sample complexity part of the proof as well
no is it.. depends..somebody say depends,
depends on what that is a paper yeah it is
there in the paper..it is there in the paper
you can look at it. And so I will stop it
here for the pac the pac complexity will come
back to all of this regret and pac and everything
when we look at the full RL problem at some
point. Now right now for the bandits we will
stop here.
IIT Madras Production
Funded by
Department of Higher Education
Ministry of Human Resource Development
Government of India
www.nptel.ac.in
Copyrights Reserved